James J. Davis Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
James J. Davis 1895-1946 (bulk 1921-1945)
MSS17913
Davis, James J. (James John), 1873-1947
13,000 items
56 containers plus 3 oversize
22.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
U. S. secretary of labor and senator from Pennsylvania. Correspondence, diaries, speeches and writings, investgation files, financial papers, scrapbooks, photographs, and printed matter relating to Davis's service as secretary of labor in three Republican presidential administrations, his tenure as senator from Pennsylvania, and as organizer and leader of the Loyal Order of Moose.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933.; Davies, Rhys J. (Rhys John), 1877-1954--Correspondence.; Davis, James J. (James John), 1873-1947.; Ferguson, Homer L. (Homer Lenoir), 1873-1953--Correspondence.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964--Correspondence.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Mellon, Andrew W. (Andrew William), 1855-1937--Correspondence.; Nye, Gerald P. (Gerald Prentice), 1892-1971.
Organizations
Loyal Order of Moose.; United States. Congress--Ethics.; United States. Congress. Senate--Elections.; United States. Congress. Senate. Select Committee on Senatorial Campaign Expenditures.; United States. Department of Labor.
Subjects
Campaign funds--Pennsylvania.; Fraternal organizations--United States.; Governmental investigations--United States.; Industrial relations--United States.; Labor--United States.; Lotteries--United States.; Political campaigns--United States.; Social security--United States.; Strikes and lockouts--United States.; Trials--United States.; Unemployment--United States.; Voluntarism--United States.
Places
Pennsylvania--Politics and government--1865-1950.; United States--Economic policy--20th century.; United States--Politics and government--1919-1933.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.
Occupations
Cabinet officers.; Senators, U.S. Congress--Pennsylvania.
Provenance
The papers of James J. Davis, U. S. secretary of labor and senator from Pennsylvania, were given to the Library of Congress by James J. Davis, Jr., Jane Schoeller, Jean A. Davis, Joan E. Hurt, and Jewel D. McGuire in 1955.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of James J. Davis are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1873, Oct. 27 Born James J. Davies, Tredagar, Wales
1881 Immigrated to the United States with his parents
1884 Apprenticed as a puddler's assistant in iron works, Sharon, Pa.
1893 1902 Moved to Elwood, Ind., and worked as city clerk
1903 1907 Recorder, Madison County, Ind.
1907 1947 Active with the Loyal Order of Moose, serving as supreme organizer and director general
1914 Married Jean Rodenbaugh
1921 1930 Secretary of labor in the Warren G. Harding, Calvin Coolidge, and Herbert Hoover administrations
1931 1945 Senator from Pennsylvania
1942 Ran unsuccessfully for govenor of Pennsylvania
1947 Administrative assistant to Senator William Langer of North Dakota
1947, Nov. 22 Died, Takoma Park, Md.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of James J. Davis (1873-1947) span the years 1895-1946, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1931-1946. The collection consists of thirteen series: Diaries, Loyal Order of Moose Correspondence, Patronage Correspondence, Political Correspondence, Family Correspondence, Special File, Financial File, Book File, Speeches and Articles, Scrapbooks and Personal Miscellany, Printed Matter, Photographs and Cartoons, and Oversize.
The Diaries include desk diaries and a register of constituents. The three correspondence series and Special File relate to political matters, constituent services, job seekers, and to his activities as a founder, organizer, and director general of the Loyal Order of Moose. Correspondents include Rhys J. Davies, Homer L. Ferguson, Herbert Hoover, and Andrew W. Mellon.
The Special File includes files on Davis's senatorial campaign in 1931; the United States Congress Senate Select Committee on Senatorial Campaign Expenditures investigation, headed by Gerald P. Nye, of his campaign expenses; and a legal case where he was the defendant, United States v. Davis, the Loyal Order of Moose lottery trial. The Speeches and Articles includes Davis's writings and speeches about labor relations, unemployment, social security, various political campaigns, and a draft of his unpublished book, "The History of Strikes."
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in thirteen series:
Diaries, 1922-1945
Loyal Order of Moose Correspondence, 1930-1940
Patronage Correspondence, 1931-1939
Political Correspondence, 1929-1944
Family Correspondence, 1943-1946
Special File, 1930-1945
Financial File, 1920-1945
Book File, 1941
Speeches and Articles, 1921-1946
Scrapbooks and Personal Miscellany, 1921-1942
Printed Matter, 1920-1945
Photographs and Cartoons, 1895-1946
Oversize, 1895-1946
Container List
- Diaries, 1922-1945 (Box 1-3)
  Scheduling desk diaries and a constituents register.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1922-1929, (8 vols.) (Box 1)
  - 1930-1940, (5 vols.) (Box 2)
  - 1939-1940, constituents register (Box 2)
  - 1941-1945, (6 vols.) (Box 3)
- Loyal Order of Moose Correspondence, 1930-1940 (Box 4-16)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - "A-B" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - "C" miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Dreyer, Fred C. (Box 5)
  - "D" miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - "E-F" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - "G" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - Hamilton, W. J. (Box 8)
  - Hart, Albert B. (Box 8)
  - Hayden, Julia (Box 8)
  - Henning, E. J. (Box 8)
  - Herrick, Lyman S. (Box 8)
  - Howell, Thomas M. (Box 8)
  - "H" miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - "I-K" miscellaneous, (4 folders) (Box 9)
  - "L" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 10)
  - "M" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - Unarranged (Box 11)
  - "M" miscellaneous topical files, (20 folders) (Box 12)
  - "N" miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - "O-Q" miscellaneous, (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - "R" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 14)
  - "Sa-Sm" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - "Sn-Sw" miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - "T-Z" miscellaneous, (7 folders) (Box 16)
- Patronage Correspondence, 1931-1939 (Box 17-23)
  Correspondence sent and received while Davis was senator from Pennsylvania with persons seeking employment in government and private industry.
  Arranged alphabetically by job seeker or position sought, as organized by Davis.
  - "Ta-To" miscellaneous, (8 folders) (Box 17)
  - "Tr-To" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 18)
  - "U" miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - United States attorney for Eastern Pennsylvania (Box 18)
  - United States Civil Service Commission (Box 18)
  - United States Circuit Court of Appeals, James J. Wilkerson (Box 19)
  - United States Circuit Court of Appeals, Ninth District (Box 19)
  - United States Coal Commission (Box 19)
  - United States Commisioner (Box 19)
  - United States Customs Court (Box 19)
  - United States District Court, Easten Pennsylvania (Box 19)
  - United States District Court, Arizona (Box 19)
  - United States District Court, Florida (Box 19)
  - United States District Court, Eastern Pennsylvania, Warren C. Graham (Box 19)
  - United States District Court, Georgia (Box 19)
  - United States District Court, Minnesota (Box 19)
  - United States marshall (Box 19)
  - United States marshall, deputy (Box 19)
  - United States secretary of treasury (Box 19)
  - United States Shipping Board (Box 19)
  - United States Supreme Court (Box 19)
  - United States surgeon general (Box 19)
  - United States Tariff Commission (Box 19)
  - United States Veterans' Bureau, Pittsburgh, Pa. (Box 20)
  - United States Veterans' Review Board (Box 20)
  - Vare Construction Co. (Box 20)
  - "V" miscellaneous (Box 20)
  - Virgin Islands governorship, Paul M. Pearson (Box 20)
  - Wagner, John E. (Box 20)
  - "Waa-Wal" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 20)
  - Washington, D. C., office (Box 21)
  - "Wan-Waz" miscellaneous (Box 21)
  - Weirbach, Annette M. (Box 21)
  - "We-Wh" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 21)
  - "Wia-Williams" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - "Williamsen-Wim" miscellaneous (Box 22)
  - "Win-Wog" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - World's Fair, Chicago, Ill. (Box 22)
  - "Wr-Wy" miscellaneous, (3 folders) (Box 22)
  - "Y-Z" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 23)
  - Unarranged, (2 folders) (Box 23)
- Political Correspondence, 1929-1944 (Box 24-28)
  Letters sent and received relating to politics and political campaigns.
  Arranged by name of correspondent or subject within chronological periods.
  - 1929-1944, (3 folders) (Box 24)
  - 1944 (Box 25)
    - "A-C" miscellaneous, (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - Davies (family nane in Wales) (Box 25)
    - "D" miscellaneous (Box 25)
    - "E-N" miscellaneous, (5 folders) (Box 26)
    - "O-W" miscellaneous, (5 folders) (Box 27)
  - 1939-1940, "A-Z" miscellaneous (Box 28)
  - 1942, campaign for governor of Pennsylvania (Box 28)
- Family Correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 29)
  Letters between Davis and his son, James J. Davis, Jr.
  - Family correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 29)
- Special File, 1930-1945 (Box 30-34)
  Legal papers, voting records, clippings, and correspondence.
  Arranged by topic.
  - Senatorial campaign expenditure committee (Box 30)
    - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 30)
      - "A-Z" (Box 30)
      - Unarranged (Box 30)
  - United States Congress Senate Select Committee on Senatorial Campaign Expenditures investigation headed by Gerald P. Nye, 1931 (Box 30)
  - United States v. Davis, Loyal Order of Moose lottery trial, 1932 (Box 31)
    - Jury (Box 31)
    - Indictment clippings (Box 31)
    - Trial clippings (Box 31)
    - Indictment correspondence, (4 folders) (Box 31)
    - Trial transcripts (Box 32)
  - Bethlehem Steel and Youngstown Sheet and Tube Co., merger, 1930 (Box 33)
  - Voting record, 71st to 77th Congresses (Box 34)
  - Guam naval base, debate and vote, 1940 (Box 34)
  - Bills sponsored by Davis, 1943 (Box 34)
- Financial File, 1920-1945 (Box 35-36)
  Personal and professional financial records.
  Unarranged.
  - Income tax, insurance policies, stocks, and bonds, (4 folders) (Box 35)
  - Notes, leases, campaign expense statememnts, expense accounts, and Loyal Order of Moose financial records (Box 36)
- Book File, 1941 (Box 37)
  Draft of Davis's unpublished book, "History of Strikes," with related correspondence.
  - Book file, 1941 (Box 37)
- Speeches and Articles, 1921-1946 (Box 38-51)
  Speeches and articles in typscript, printed, or draft format.
  - 1921, (2 vols.) (Box 38)
  - 1922-1923, (2 vols.) (Box 39)
  - 1924, (2 vols.) (Box 40)
  - 1925, (2 vols.) (Box 41)
  - 1926 Jan.-1927 May, (2 vols.) (Box 42)
  - 1927 June-1928 June, (2 vols.) (Box 43)
  - 1928 July-1929 Apr., (2 vols.) (Box 44)
  - 1929 May-1929 Dec., (2 vols.) (Box 45)
  - 1930 Jan.-May (Box 46)
  - 1930, May-Nov., (2 vols.) (Box 47)
  - 1922-1930, (3 folders) (Box 48)
  - 1924-1937, (3 folders) (Box 49)
  - 1938-1944, 3 folders) (Box 50)
  - Loyal Order of Moose speeches, 1929-1937 (Box 50)
- Scrapbooks and Personal Miscellany, 1921-1942 (Box 51-53)
  Scrapbooks, a copy of Davis's death certificate, certificates of appreciation, a gavel, and miscellaneous material.
  Material chronologically arranged within scrapbooks. Personal miscellany unarranged.
  - Scrapbooks (Box 51)
    - 1921-1924 (Box 51)
    - 1922-1923, 1928, (2 vols.) (Box 52)
    - 1942 See Oversize (Box 52)
  - Personal miscellany. (Box 53)
- Printed Matter, 1920-1949 (Box 54-55)
  Clippings, pamphlets, and magazines.
  - Printed matter, 1920-1949 (Box 54-55)
- Photographs and Cartoons, 1895-1946 (Box 56)
  Photographs and political cartoons, 1895-1946
  - Photographs and political cartoons, 1895-1946 See also Oversize (Box 56)
- Oversize, 1895-1946 (Box OV 1-OV 3)
  Scrapbooks, photographs, and cartoons.
  Arranged according to the series and files from which the material was removed.
  - Scrapbooks, 1942 (Container 52) (Box OV 1)
    - Feb.-May (Box OV 1)
    - May-June (Box OV 2)
  - Photographs and cartoons, 1895-1946 (Container 56) (Box OV 3)